<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vindication of A. Cresner, school-master in Long-Acre, from the aspersions of A. Pulton, Jesuit and school-master in the Savoy together with some account of his discourse with Mr. Meredith. Imprimatur, Octob. 24. 1687. Hic liber cui titulus The vindication of A. Cresner, &amp;c. H. Maurice Reverendissimo in Christo P.D. Wilhelmo Archiep. Cant. à Sacris.</title>
            <author>Chresner, A.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80796</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6885</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202667</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896094</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896094</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153885</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80796)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153885)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1525:4; 2386:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vindication of A. Cresner, school-master in Long-Acre, from the aspersions of A. Pulton, Jesuit and school-master in the Savoy together with some account of his discourse with Mr. Meredith. Imprimatur, Octob. 24. 1687. Hic liber cui titulus The vindication of A. Cresner, &amp;c. H. Maurice Reverendissimo in Christo P.D. Wilhelmo Archiep. Cant. à Sacris.</title>
                  <author>Chresner, A.</author>
                  <author>Pulton, A. (Andrew), 1654-1710.</author>
                  <author>Meredith, Edward, 1648-1689?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Ric. Chiswell at the Rose and Crown in St. Paul's Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXVII. [1687]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The words "The vindication ... Cresner, &amp;c." which follow "Hic liber cui titulus" in lines 13-14 of title are enclosed in square brackets.</note>
                  <note>A variant of the edition with "A. Cressner," in line 4 of title and lacking errata at the bottom of p. 14.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Union Theological Seminary Library; Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153885:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VINDICATION OF A. Creſner, School-Maſter in LONG-ACRE, From the Aſperſions of <hi>A. P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LTON,</hi> Jeſuit and School-Maſter in the SAVOY; Together With ſome Account of His Diſcourſe with Mr. MEREDITH.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>Imprimatur,</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Octob.</hi> 24. 1687.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Hic Liber cui Titulus</hi> [The Vindication of <hi>A. Creſner,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>H. Maurice Reverendiſſimo in Chriſto P. D.</hi> Wilhelmo <hi>Archiep.</hi> Cant. <hi>à Sacris.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Ric. Chiſwell</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. MDCLXXXVII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:153885:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153885:2"/>
            <head>THE VINDICATION OF <hi>A. CRESNER,</hi> School-Maſter in LONG-ACRE.</head>
            <p>
               <q>HERE a pleaſant School-Maſter di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Pulton</hi>'s Aſperſions in his Narrative.</note> the Auditory, with a Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture (as he pretended) of the Bleſſed Trinity, which he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, with wry Mouths, and many antick Geſtures; upon this I told him of God's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in the ſhape of an Old Man, and that we might Picture him, ſo we meant not to delineate him <hi>ſub ſpecie propriâ.</hi> I turn'd to the Doctor, and preſs'd my fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd Argument, but the School-Maſter continuing to give Diverſion to the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and throw in Impertinent Queſtions, I bid him be ſilent, ſaying, I came not to Diſpute
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153885:3"/>
with a Buffoon, but a Doctor.</q> Thus far our Diſputant, to which I Anſwer;</p>
            <p>That our Jeſuit cannot be Ignorant of the Method <hi>A. C.</hi> us'd in his Diſcourſe with him, without putting <note place="margin">A Vindication of <hi>A. C.</hi>
               </note> violence upon his Underſtanding, and wilfully reſolving to Miſ-repreſent his Adverſarie's Arguments whatever it coſt him. He tells us <hi>A. C.</hi> was pleaſant, and indeed ſo he was, and he that could keep his Temper amidſt a company of ſuch ſingular Arguments, as <hi>M. P.</hi> vented in defence of his Cauſe, he that could be ſo grave, as to deny himſelf the liberty of a Smile, at the ſingularity of M. <hi>P</hi>'s Reaſonings, hath really grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhare of Mortification, than ever <hi>A. C.</hi> could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to. But our Jeſuit may Object, What had <hi>A. C.</hi> to do, to ſpeak in a Cauſe he had nothing to do with, was not the Doctor able to defend his Religion, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out borrowing the Aſſiſtance of a By-ſtander, who yet appear'd impertinent enough in what he ſaid? As for the Impertinency of it, that ſhall come in in its place; 'twill I hope be ſufficient to rectifie Miſapprehenſions of this Matter, and to juſtifie the procedure of <hi>A. C.</hi> if the Reader be acquainted with the Motives that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluenc'd him to ſpeak his Thoughts of what was ſaid by our Diſputant. The occaſion then was this.</p>
            <p>The Reverend <hi>D. T.</hi> being ſometimes engaged with <note place="margin">The occaſion of <hi>A. C</hi>'s ſpeaking to Mr. <hi>Pulton.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>M. M.</hi> who ſate at his Left Hand, and who would ſeveral times interpoſe with private Queſtions of his own, though <hi>D. T.</hi> was never ſo cloſely engag'd with our Diſputant; 'twas the little Equity that appear'd in this ſort of conduct that urg'd <hi>A. C.</hi> to deliver his Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of the Subject diſputed of, but ſtill with reſpect to the very foul play us'd by our Adverſaries. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to all this? why truly juſt nothing,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153885:3"/>
but on the contrary would inſinuate to the World, that all that <hi>A. C.</hi> did in relation to the Conference, was abrupt and without neceſſity: I muſt confeſs if our Jeſuit's bare ſaying all this was true, was ſufficient to prove it ſo; it were an unpardonable Preſumption in any Man to go about to perſwade the World into a contrary Opinion; but becauſe it is hop'd that <hi>A. C.</hi> may find better luck, than to be ſo unmercifully uſed, he comes now to give the World a true repreſentation of his own Deportment at the Conference.</p>
            <p>And Firſt, <hi>A. C.</hi> cannot forbear wondring, at our <note place="margin">The true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of the Words and Actions which Mr. <hi>P.</hi> hath ſo much miſrepreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; together with their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</note> Jeſuit's forwardneſs to Inſinuate to the World, as though <hi>A. C.</hi> produc'd a reſemblance of the Bleſſed Trinity (which is delineated in their own <hi>Breviary,</hi> ſet out by the Authorities of <hi>Pius</hi> the <hi>5th.</hi> and <hi>Clement 8th.)</hi> abruptly and without any regard to the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Subject diſputed of; which if it had been ſo (as it was not) it were but equitable and fair to follow our Authors Example, who firſt pull'd out of his Pocket a <hi>Breviary</hi> to help his Memory, which would certainly have been at a loſs without it. Is then our Author become ſo Criminal, that it is dangerous for any Man to follow his Example, without being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd for it? for otherwiſe, how comes the ſame Action to be both prudent and ſafe in our Diſputant, and yet ridiculous and dangerous in another, when the external Circumſtances that produc'd that Action were both the ſame. M. <hi>P.</hi> pull'd his <hi>Breviary</hi> out of his Pocket to aſſiſt his own Memory, and his Adverſary produces another <hi>Breviary</hi> to relieve his; this is really the Caſe: yet 'tis this Action our Jeſuit takes ſo much pains to diſcredit; if there be any thing indecent in the Action, our Diſputant ought to have given a better Example. Our Jeſuit hath here a great mind to be thought in the right, and therefore ſays, that what
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153885:4"/>
               <hi>A. C.</hi> had ſhown him, he pretended to be the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of the Bleſſed Trinity. But what does our Diſputant mean by pretended? not ſure that he himſelf had no other way of knowing it to be ſo, than <hi>A. C</hi>'s bare affirming that it was ſuch a reſemblance, and yet there can be no other Senſe put upon this Word, than is here put upon it; for <hi>A. C.</hi> ſhew'd it him (the Jeſuit) who look'd on it, endeavouring withal to juſtifie the Practice of their Church in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, without offering at any other way of doing it, than by producing that Text in <hi>Daniel Cap.</hi> 7. <hi>ver.</hi> 9. which I ſhall ſpeak to in its place. But then,</p>
            <p>Secondly, This pulling out the <hi>Breviary</hi> hath yet a greater Juſtification attending it, than M. <hi>P.</hi> is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to make the World believe it hath, and which if prov'd, may go near to relieve this Action from Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinency. Our Diſputant having objected to D. <hi>T.</hi> (who ſpake of the ſhare the <hi>Greeks</hi> ought to have in our Belief as well as other Churches, in their hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down the Bible to us (as a part at leaſt of the Univerſal Church) that the Teſtimony of the <hi>Greeks</hi> could not be rely'd upon, becauſe of their denial of the Proceſſion of the Third Perſon of the Trinity from the two Firſt. D. <hi>T.</hi> going to anſwer our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputant, was interrupted by M <hi>M.</hi> In this Interval <hi>A. C.</hi> ſeeing the Jeſuit diſengag'd, told him, That as for the <hi>Greeks,</hi> their Diſpute was about Phraſes, and that they were agreed in Senſe; further adding, that upon that ſcore, they were far more juſtifiable in an unwilful miſtake of a Term and Mode of Expreſſion, than the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, who brought down the Glory of the Adorable Trinity, into the pitiful reſemblance of a Picture, thus doing more miſchief by their unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable Practiſes, than theſe <hi>Greeks</hi> by their Doctrine: whereupon <hi>A. C.</hi> turn'd to the place, where this delinea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was, and ſhow'd it our Jeſuit.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:153885:4"/>
And now let the World judge where the imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency of this action lay, and whether it was half ſo ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous as our Diſputants making uſe of his <hi>Speculum,</hi> where his Leſſon was prick'd ready to his hand, inſtead of anſwering like a Schollar that had undertaken the Cauſe of his Church. But were theſe all the imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Actions <hi>A. C.</hi> is charged with? No, our Diſputant hath not only diſcover'd Impertinency, but a great deal of rudeneſs in <hi>A. C</hi>'s. procedure: but pray let us hear what 'tis; why he tells the World, <q>That <hi>A. C.</hi> ſhew'd him the Picture with wry Mouths and many An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Geſtures.</q> Why truly this is a heavy Charge, and little beſeeming a Proteſtant who had the honour to ſpeak in the defence of his Religion, which, if true, would go near to make him reſolve never to venture in the Defence of his Religion, if he could not do it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſo many guilty Actions. But what if this Charge ſhould prove (as I am afraid it will) to be falſe, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Calumny, what will become of <hi>M. P</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and that mighty Eſteem he hath acquired a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his own Party, of being ſo well vers'd in all thoſe Qualifications, that are requiſite to conſummate an able Diſputant? I am afraid <hi>M. P.</hi> is grown a little unwary of late, that he is ſo ready to venture his Reputation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſidering what may be the Conſequences which will attend the proof of his unfair dealing. But per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps our Jeſuite may not be ſatisfied, unleſs it be prov'd that what he charges <hi>A. C.</hi> with, is very far from being true, which I ſhall endeavour to do, that I may ſatisfie our Jeſuite's longing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> Then I anſwer, <hi>A. C.</hi> is very ſure he never kept a ſtricter guard upon his Actions, than at this Diſpute, as not being influenc'd in the leaſt by any Paſſion, though never more provok'd than at this time, being by our Diſputant call'd by a very hard Name, which, had <hi>A. C.</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:153885:5"/>
been inclin'd to any Paſſion, in the Diſpute, that unchriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an uſage of our Jeſuite, might have juſtified the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant one: But on the contrary, <hi>A. C.</hi> mildly reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That as for unkind Words, he was reſolv'd he would not make uſe of any, that he would come behind our Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite in nothing, but in that ſort of Language which he was too well acquainted with, to begin to uſe it now: adding moreover, that he would do our Jeſuite all the kindneſs that lay in his power, having always that notable Saying of a Worthy Gentleman in his mind, <q>That it was the method of Charity to ſuffer without re-action</q> Dares our Diſputant ſay that I gave him the leaſt il Word? I confeſs part of this Diſcourſe was uſed with our Jeſuite after the Diſpute of the Counſels of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> and <hi>Trent;</hi> but however, this is ſufficient to prove the mildneſs <hi>A. C.</hi> uſed towards our Diſputant, in that there was moſt part of this ſpoken after <hi>M. M.</hi> had en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deavoured to juſtifie <hi>M. P.</hi> in this ſort of Rude<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2ly.</hi> The Aequanimity of <hi>A. C</hi>'s Deportment under theſe Circumſtances, may be partly gueſs'd from the little di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſturbance, the weakneſs of our Diſputant's Argument could give an Adverſary; but whether they were ſo or no, the Conference will beſt diſcover. Men are uſually calm and ſedate, when they have an anſwer ready to the Objections of their Antagoniſt. And on the contrary, 'tis then they fly into paſſion, when any thing preſſes them that they cannot anſwer; and that I ſuppoſe made our Jeſuite (inſtead of anſwering <hi>A. C</hi>'s Objections) call him <hi>Buffoon,</hi> unleſs this laſt Word hath ſome extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſenſe in it, which no Mortal, beſides our Diſputant, hath yet been able to pick out of it; and if it hath, <hi>M. P.</hi> ought to have decyphered it, that the World may be taught for the future, to anſwer by whole-ſale, without uſing that tedious way of twenty Words, when one will
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153885:5"/>
do: but if no man can find any thing in the Word, but virulency and bitterneſs, as indeed they cannot, how can our Diſputant evade the force of that Reproof the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend D. <hi>T.</hi> gave him, upon his uſing it to <hi>A C?</hi> But what then? Did <hi>M. P.</hi> give <hi>A. C.</hi> no other anſwer? Why truly yes; he told <hi>A. C.</hi> That the Repreſentation of the Trinity was no ſuch ſtrange thing, ſeeing that in <hi>Daniel,</hi> God had appeared in the ſhape of an old Man, and that we might Picture him, ſo we mean not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineate him <hi>ſub ſpecie propriâ.</hi> To this <hi>A. C.</hi> anſwered (which our Adverſary hath conceal'd) That as for the Text before us, what this Prophet ſaw, was only in a Viſion, which was a Repreſentation of Gods coming to Judgment, and fitted only to that particular occaſion; and therefore ought not to be proſtituted to all intents and purpoſes whatſoever: and then for the lawfulneſs of repreſenting God, provided it was not meant to do it <hi>ſub ſpecie propriâ, A. C.</hi> anſwers now, (he confeſſes he did not anſwer to this laſt part of the Objection at the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference) Any one may ſee (if he will but take a little pains) the vanity of this diſtinction; for if God's Image be not given us <hi>ſub ſpecie propriâ,</hi> with relation to his own Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, 'tis no more the Image of God, but the Sign of his Power which is repreſented in the above-mentioned Chapter of <hi>Daniel;</hi> his Throne was like the fiery flame, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But ſuppoſe all our Diſputant ſays were true, what comfort could it be to a poor Soul, who is charged with diſhonouring God, who is Infinite, by repreſenting him by an Image that is Finite, and terminated by viſible Dimenſions, to be told by M. <hi>P.</hi> that he do's not diſhonour God, becauſe he hath no intention to repreſent him <hi>ſub ſpecie propriâ?</hi> But becauſe <hi>A. C.</hi> ſaid not this at the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>efernce, he does intend to add but one Word, or two more: And firſt, That he might here obſerve, that if it were granted, that we might picture each of the Three
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153885:6"/>
Perſons of the B. Trinity apart; that this could be no ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument at all, for it's reſembling it (the Trinity), becauſe ſuch Reſemblances does not only make Three Perſons, but Three Gods; ſuch Images as theſe, repreſent not only a diſtinction of Perſons, but a diverſity of Subſtance. I leave our Jeſuite to think of this; for it is not <hi>A. C</hi>'s. meaning to enlarge on this Subject, as intending only to give a Relation of what he ſaid at the Conference. Our Diſputant goes on, telling us, That the School-Maſter (meaning <hi>A. C.)</hi> ſtill interpoſing with <hi>impertinent Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, M. P.</hi> bad him be ſilent; but I would fain know of our Jeſuite, which of thoſe Queſtions were <hi>Imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent.</hi> If he means by this Word, that the <hi>Queſtions A. C.</hi> asked, were not at all to our Jeſuits purpoſe, which was to make the <hi>Spectators</hi> believe, he was very knowing in thoſe things he talked of with ſo much free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and of which, all unbyaſs'd perſons at the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly found he was very ignorant: <hi>A. C.</hi> is very ready to confeſs that he was impertinent enough; but becauſe (it may be) our Diſputant may take impertinency in it's moſt ordinary ſence, <hi>A. C.</hi> need not clear himſelf here, becauſe it is already done to his hand in the Body of the Conference, whither I refer the Reader for ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in this point. D. <hi>T.</hi> finding <hi>M. P.</hi> to be very ignorant of common Church-Hiſtory, which he perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Anſwers our Jeſuite made him, D. <hi>T.</hi> preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>M. P.</hi> about the Councel of <hi>Lateran:</hi> This Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant having firſt nam'd this Councel himſelf (where the term Tranſubſtantiation was invented, to expreſs the Corporeal Preſence, after the year 1200, after it had been broached by <hi>Paſchaſius Radbertus,</hi> in the year 818.) but while this was asking, <hi>M. M.</hi> pulled D. <hi>T.</hi> to be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied about ſome Queſtions he had to propoſe. <hi>A. C.</hi> (ſeeing D. <hi>T.</hi> engaged with <hi>M. M.)</hi> took up the Jeſuit, and made an end of what D. <hi>T.</hi> had began by asking our Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153885:6"/>
ſome important Queſtions, which concerned the <hi>Lateran</hi> Council, which no Perſons (that had but the leaſt knowledge of this Council by any other way, than that of Quotation) could be ignorant of: As, How many Fathers there were, who preſided in it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To the firſt he anſwers, a Thouſand, and to the laſt, nothing. In all our Jeſuit's Accuſations of <hi>A. C.</hi> we have not one word of what was anſwered, neither of what <hi>A. C.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed occaſionally when ſtanding by D. <hi>T.</hi> nor what was urged in the laſt Room betwixt our Diſputant and <hi>A. C.</hi> about the contradictions of the Two Councils, <hi>Conſtance</hi> and <hi>Trent,</hi> upon the queſtion of the Pope's Superiority. All this our Jeſuit hath quite ſlipt over, either wilfully or forgetfully, I ſhall not determine which: If the firſt, our Diſputant hath unworthily prevaricated in the cauſe of God, and render'd the Proteſtants cauſe weak and impotent, which I am ſure is not the part of a Gentleman, nor a Scholar: if the laſt, it had been the part of a prudent perſon to have taken ſurer meaſures, to have acted more cautiouſly in a thing of this Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, before he had ventured to have treated <hi>A. C.</hi> with ſo much virulency and contempt: but to prevent all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſentation, I ſhall annex the Diſcourſe <hi>A. C.</hi> had both with <hi>M. M.</hi> and our Diſputant, at the end of this Paper, which, according to the exacteſt care I could take, of nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther adding any thing on <hi>A.C</hi>'s ſide, or omitting on his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, was thus: When the Queſtion of [How the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants could tell that the Bible they uſed, was really what they, (the Proteſtants) thought it to be, the Word of God,] <note place="margin">An Account of the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt M. <hi>M.</hi> and <hi>A. C.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſional.</note> had been canvaſs'd ſome while, <hi>M. M.</hi> ariſing, went to the other end of the Room, whither <hi>A. C.</hi> follow'd him, deſiring ſome ſatisfaction about the prohibition in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Commandment; <hi>A. C.</hi> telling him, that this way of worſhipping of God, and the Saints (beſides the utter unlawfulneſs of worſhipping the latter, either ultimately
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153885:7"/>
or relatively) by Repreſentations, they brought down the Glory of Holineſs, which conſiſted in the Excellency of inward Diſpoſitions, to the contemptible lowneſs of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beholden, for the moſt indiſtracted part of our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion to the ſight of an Image; which is a readier way to advance, than to cure our Diſtraction; that it was much more agreeable to the Precepts of the Goſpel, to ſerve God after his own Preſcription, who being a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, our Saviour tells us, <hi>muſt be worſhipped in Spirit and in Truth.</hi> M. <hi>M.</hi> anſwer'd, That we were Finite Creatures, and what conceptions we had of God, could be no more than finite neither; and therefore why not by an Image? The firſt part of this I granted, but muſt not, I told him, allow of his Inference, telling him, we ought to come as near to the Nature of God as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, in our Devotions to him; but that would beſt be done, by a Worſhip, abſtracted from all material repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations of him. To this M. <hi>M.</hi> anſwered, Well, well; and from thence began to preach me a Moral Lecture, which I heartily thank'd him for; and ſo we parted for that time, he to the Converſation of ſome Women of his Acquaintance, and <hi>A. C.</hi> to the place of Diſpute; whither he went ſome time after to <hi>M. M.</hi> again, who was then at the Window; but there happening a little time after, a Diſcourſe about the Confeſſional, <hi>(A. C.</hi> does not exactly remember for what Reaſons the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was ſtarted) <hi>A. C.</hi> asked <hi>M. M.</hi> What if a Perſon that was a Traytor to the Kingdom or State, of which he was a Subject, and was actually in Conſpiracy with others againſt that Kingdom or State; if this Traytor ſhould come, and reveal this Conſpiracy to a Prieſt, by way of Confeſſion, muſt that Prieſt reveal the horrid Secret or not? To which <hi>M. M.</hi> reply'd, No; that Prieſt muſt not diſcloſe it. What<hi>!</hi> replyed <hi>A. C.</hi> and muſt ſuch a Kingdom or State, be involv'd in Blood and ruine, for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153885:7"/>
want of ſuch an Obedience as Indiſpenſibly obliges e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Subject of what Capacity ſoever, not to be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in his utmoſt endeavours for the preſervation of that Kingdom or State he owes all the Happineſſes of Life to? To this M. <hi>M.</hi> reply'd, That all this was nothing, all that the Prieſt could do in this matter, was to deny him Abſolution, if he did not Repent. And is this (repeated <hi>A. C.)</hi> all the ſecurity a King or Kingdom muſt expect from you in ſuch a juncture of Affairs? Is not the Prieſt (by taking Methods like theſe) actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally enrolled in the Number of the Conſpiratours? are not they as ſure of him in relation to ſecreſie, as of the greateſt Deſperado in all their Cabal? Is it very likely, that Fellows deſperately reſolv'd to do ſuch barbarous Acts of Wickedneſs, will be much mov'd or concern'd at your denial of Abſolution to them? To this <hi>M. M.</hi> reply'd, That <hi>A. C.</hi> was out in his Conceptions, for the Prieſt did not help the Conſpirators by theſe means. And ſeeing him ſtop there, <hi>A. C.</hi> anſwer'd, And is it poſſible that ſuch an Ingenious Man as M. <hi>M.</hi> can be guilty of ſo great an abſurdity, as to ſay (as you do) that the Prieſt does not help the Conſpirators, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he does not actually make ſome endeavours himſelf towards the promotion of ſuch a deed of darkneſs? To all which <hi>A. C.</hi> could have notihng re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, but, That if the Prieſt did deny him Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, he had done his Duty. After which <hi>A. C.</hi> had no further Diſcourſe with M. <hi>M.</hi> nor any other, till a part of the Company retired into another Room, whither <hi>A. C.</hi> follow'd them, and engag'd himſelf with the Jeſuit, about the Decrees of ſome later Councils, as <note place="margin">An Account of the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt our Jeſuit and <hi>A. C.</hi>
               </note> thoſe of <hi>Conſtance</hi> and <hi>Trent,</hi> againſt which he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to prove a Contradiction in their Decrees; the firſt of theſe ſetting up the Council above the Pope; the latter deciding the direct contrary, ſetting up the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153885:8"/>
Pope above the Council. <hi>A. C.</hi> affirm'd, That this firſt Council could not be Infallible, becauſe it had not been Conven'd by a Lawful Pope, but had aſſembled it ſelf at the Sollicitation of Chriſtian Princes, and by the ſole Authority and Power of the College of Cardinals: Now if a Council cannot be Infallible without the Pope in Perſon or by his Legates, then it is plain this Council was not Infallible, becauſe there was no true Pope in being; for it conven'd to condem three falſe ones; now were the Acts during the Interval of this Council Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible or not? To which M. <hi>P.</hi> anſwer'd in the affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive. To which <hi>A. C.</hi> reply'd, What, without a Pope? To this our Diſputant ſaid, That this ſignified little, ſo long as the Pope confirm'd what the Council had done; and when <hi>A. C.</hi> reply'd, That the queſtion was not about the Infallibility of the Decrees after Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation; but whither the Deciſions of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil before Confirmation were Obligatory upon Mens Conſciences, ſo as to oblige all Perſons of what Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſoever, to act in purſuance of them; and if they were, then ſuch ſubmiſſion muſt be due to them, by vertue of ſome Infallible Authority enjoyning ſuch ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; but the Authority that enjoyn'd the Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Canons of this Council, was not Infallible, becauſe it wanted an Eſſential part of its Infallibility, <hi>viz.</hi> the Preſence of the Pope in Perſon, or by his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gats; thus theſe Qualifications being wanting, the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity that exacted Obedience to their Decrees, was fallible; and upon that ſcore, could not indiſpenſibly oblige any Individual Member of their Church to ſubmit to it with an implicit Obedience. M. <hi>P.</hi> ſtill urged the Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation (which the Pope gave the Acts of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil) for their being infallible, and therefore Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally Obligatory. <hi>A. C.</hi> ſeeing our Diſputant could not be made to drop this Inſignificant ſhift, asked him
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153885:8"/>
what that was the Pope confirmed? an Error? For amongſt the Acts of this Council, the Supremacy of a Council above a Pope was actually decreed; but the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> which came afterward, decreed juſt the contrary: Now one of theſe Councils was certainly miſtaken, for their Canons (which reſpect this Article) are form'd in direct contrariety to each other; this Council coming under debate, <hi>A. C.</hi> ask'd our Jeſuit, What he thought of the Decree made at <hi>Trent</hi> about the Forfeiture that Princes were to ſuffer, in Caſe they ſhould permit any Duellings in their Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories? The Import of the Decree in <hi>Engliſh</hi> runs in this Senſe, in ſhort, <hi>viz.</hi> That if the places on which the Duels were fought, be Fief Lands, they ſhall Eſcheat to the Lords of the Fiefe; I do not exactly remember whether our Diſputant objected that Clauſe <hi>quod ab Eccleſia obtinent,</hi> which implies that the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture ſhould only be of thoſe Lands that were hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the Church; and if our Jeſuit did object this, (becauſe I would not omit any thing material he ſaid in his defence) <hi>A. C.</hi> anſwers in the Words of a late Ingenious Gentleman, who ſays, That that Clauſe, <hi>quod ab Eccleſia obtinent,</hi> was inſerted into the Decree, only to hinder the oppoſition that would have been made by the Ambaſſadors of Kings and Princes, who were preſent in that Council, and who would never have let paſs a Decree ſo deſtructive of their Maſter's Intereſts; from all which <hi>A. C.</hi> Inferred, He that can by Virtue of ſome Right reſiding in himſelf, diſpoſe (upon any pretence whatſoever) of a parcel of Land as big as this Room (ſpeaking of the Room he was in) may take away a Province, and he that may <hi>Jure ſuo</hi> take away a Province; may rifle a Prince of his Dominions; but that is depoſing of them: To which M. <hi>P.</hi> reply'd, No ſuch thing, for if my Prince ſhall lay upon me a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153885:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
moderate Tax, hath therefore that Prince a Right to all I have? To which <hi>A. C.</hi> anſwer'd, No, adding, That what M. <hi>P.</hi> urg'd as a Simile, was not at all like the thing we diſputed of; for the Queſtion was not of the Power of Princes over their Subjects, but the Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of the Eccleſiaſtical State, over that of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil one, without this latter States leave; to which M. <hi>P.</hi> reply'd All good Princes ought to conſent to the Deciſions of the Church; But anſwer'd, <hi>A. C.</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thoſe good Princes are not in a very good Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour (as 'tis ten to one if they are, when the Church decides ſo favourably for her ſelf) and have no mind to recede from their Right to any part or parts of their Dominions, of which they are the true owners; muſt they be diſpoſſeſs'd of their Rights againſt their Wills? To all which <hi>A. C.</hi> had no other anſwer than this, or much to the ſame Effect, <hi>viz.</hi> That in ſuch a Caſe the Church had power to decide in favour of it ſelf. Well, ſays <hi>A C.</hi> to our Jeſuit, if the Caſe be ſo, I am ſatisfied; and withal turned himſelf away, and had ſome Diſcourſe with a Gentleman by the Bed ſide.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>On the Title for</hi> Creſner, <hi>r.</hi> Creſſener. <hi>pag.</hi> 2. <hi>line</hi> 12. <hi>for</hi> greater <hi>r.</hi> a greater, <hi>p.</hi> 7. <hi>l.</hi> 30. <hi>for</hi> Term and Mode, <hi>r.</hi> Term or Mode.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
